JOE: The use of parental controls
with online media, can solve many
problems with regards to protecting
children with autism, from
unpleasant or inappropriate content.
This, however, will probably only work
short term, because the individual may
become more proficient at bypassing these
controls, as they get older, especially
if they are good with technology.
Parents may also stop monitoring
the children as they feel that
there isn’t a need anymore.
BETH: Most of the time the use of
IT, video games and social media in
moderation, can be positive activities, as
long as sensible guidelines are followed.
In the same way safety checks
are done when children and young
people are out and about, then the
same should apply on the internet.
However, when is an individual with
autism, deemed old enough to make
their own choices and to be trusted
online, should parents still enforce
their controls on adults because of
a perceived need to protect them?
JOE: It can be more successful if
parents share internet experiences with
their children, having regular open
discussions with them about their safety
in general, but especially online.
As the internet means so much to many
autistic children, parents taking an
interest seems natural and supportive and
a way to develop the parent-child bond,
rather than a way of spying on them.
BETH: Addiction especially can be
a concern for parents of autistic
children and adults, as their
obsessive nature can lead to internet
gaming and social media dependency.
An individual with autism may often
find sanctuary from the real world,
in an alternate world that appears
safe, and offers an opportunity to
meet and communicate comfortably in
their own home with people more like
themselves, with the same interests.
JOE: Many individuals with autism who
suffer loneliness and isolation due
to problems with social interaction,
can find communicating via a computer
a much less stressful and a more
enjoyable way of maintaining friendships.
Social media allows for an almost
instant response and can be
helpful in communicating with
other individuals with autism and
their families, friends and carers.
BETH: It enables charities and
organisations offering help and
advice to reach people more easily
with online support available often
24/7, not just during office hours.
The internet can have both positive and
negative impacts on individuals with
autism and their families, however If
used appropriately and in moderation, can
be of great benefit in terms of offering
a different form of socialisation.
It can also be beneficial in
terms of accessing information
and being able to share interests.
JOE: Negative things can happen using
social media and the internet as they can
in all aspects of life, but as long as
individuals with autism are made aware
and prepared for those risks, they can
develop the tools to cope with them.
BETH: The positive thing about
computers and the internet is that
they are potentially the greatest
asset for individuals with autism,
opening up a new world of potential
friends, opportunity and employment.
The internet is here to stay so it is
important to make it a positive and
beneficial experience for all, however
they can most effectively use it.